ARLO BELSHEE

PRINCIPAL SOFTWARE ENGINEER AND MENTOR



Profile

I speed up my teams. We write fewer bugs and take less time to get stories done. This happens because I know how to reduce technical debt in ways that have immediate positive return during the current story. I both do these myself and teach others.



Selected publications

How I Design Systems

The No Mocks Book (2012), and Architecture — Scaling Design (2013)

I build systems with less coupling than many people. The key aspects are higher coupling and conceptual integrity, architecting the people as part of the system, along with use of more testable architectural patterns. These articles provide examples.

http://arlobelshee.com/the-no-mocks-book/

http://arlobelshee.com/architecture-scaling-design/

How I Prevent Bugs

I Find Bugs Too Boring to Write (2017)

My teams get to Zero Bugs, whether I'm their manager or a member-leader. This talk discusses my reproducible approach.

https://www.deconstructconf.com/2017/arlo-belshee-i-find-bugs-too-boring-to-write

How I Help Teams Improve Their Practices

Agile Engineering Fluency (2016)

The hardest part of change is helping people see what they don't know and have never experienced. Here's how I solve that for engineering improvements.

Agile Leadership

https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=o6rQNwYLy6A

Skills

Mend Legacy Code

systemic flaws as a series of

small, safe changes. Mentor

Safely modify unfamiliar

code quickly. Address

others to do same.

Lead teams' ability to responsibly own their outcomes. Mentor individuals and groups

towards increased autonomy and inclusiveness.

System Architecture

Smoothly transition large systems between architectures. Guide teams on architectural choices and paths to get there.

Technical

JavaScript / C# / C++ / Python	XP / Lean / Kanban	Microservices
OData / REST	People Management	DevOps Enablement
SQL	Emotion Dynamics	Incremental Rewrites
TDD / Refactoring / Paring	Vertical Leadership Development	Hexagonal Architecture

Selected Experience

Tableau Principal Agile Development Coach

2016-2019

No other person in the world has shifted my perspective on software development, and software development organizations, as much as Arlo. He lives inside a worldview of the future that most

haven't glimpsed, some haven't grasped, and even fewer see how to get there.

- James Baker, Principal Technical Advisor, Tableau Software

Microsoft 2011-2014

Senior Software Developer, Engineering Excellence

Arlo was a key partner in helping the Microsoft Office organization transition to an agile continuous delivery model, with a focus on refactoring legacy code and getting it under test.

I sat in on a lot of his "mob sessions", where we'd bring in a piece of code and have Arlo coach us on how to get it under test. My favorite saying from Arlo was "your bug database should be the corner of your whiteboard...and it should be empty" :)

- Dheeraj Sarpangal, Principal Group Engineering Manager, Microsoft

Silver Platter Software Architect

1999-2003

Arlo's facility with programming language concepts and architectural design is superlative and working with him every day quickly inspired me to become an expert and approach programming with rigor and precision.

Six years later, I still miss programming with Arlo.

- Jon Stewart, Vice President, Solutions Development, Stroz Friedberg

Education

Pomona College - Claremont, California Math major

Arlo Belshee — $\underline{\text{arlo@belshee.com}}$ — (503) - 875-1234